Mss.Rec.31 Mss.Rec.31
American Philosophical Society
Ahtna Texts Recorded in Copper Center, Alaska
1958
Mss.Rec.31
American Philosophical Society
8.0 Reel(s)
Ahtna songs and stories recorded in Copper Center, Alaska by Frederica de Laguna in 1958. Includes numerous interviews on autobiographical topics, explanations of Ahtna songs, sleep doctors, and traditional narratives. Also includes vocabulary related to kinship terms. Songs include potlatch songs, love songs, drinking songs, and songs of Tlingit origin.
8 sound tape reels (7 hr., 31 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
McClellan, Catharine
Conditions Governing Access
Permission required for access to materials. Please consult the Manuscripts Librarian for details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Frederica De Laguna, 1959.
Related Archival Materials
Related material in the American Council of Learned Societies. Committee on Native American Languages (497.3 B63c).
Ahtena Indians; Ahtena language; Indians of North America--Alaska; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Interview with Martha Jackson, 1958-07-11; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:27; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    Scope and Contents note
    Largely concerns kinship terms. Part 1 of 5.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Ahtena Indians--Kinship; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Anthropological linguistics; Copper Center (Alaska)
  - Interview with Martha Jackson, 1958-07-11; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:25; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    Largely concerns kinship terms. Part 2 of 5.
  - Interview with Martha Jackson, 1958-07-11; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:33:17; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    Largely concerns kinship terms. Part 3 of 5.
  - Interview with Martha Jackson, 1958-07-11; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:51; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    Largely concerns kinship terms. Part 4 of 5.
  - Interview with Martha Jackson, 1958-07-11; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:15; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    Largely concerns kinship terms. Part 5 of 5.
  - Fanny Stanfield: Copper River Song; SARani (Crow) dance song; nAlbei (Seagull) dance song; Drinking song, 1958-07-11; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:36; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johns, Harry; McClellan, Catharine; Stanfield, Fanny
    Copper River Song -- SARani (Crow) and nAlbei (Seagull) dance song -- Interrupted song -- Drinking Song
    Ahtena dance; Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
  - Arthur and Martha Jackson, kin terms, 1958-07-11; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:54:25; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Arthur; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    At beginning of recording the date is misidentified as 1954.
  - Martha Jackson, 1958-08-16; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:40; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
    Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Potlatch--Alaska; Shamanism--Alaska
  - Martha Jackson, 1958-08-16; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:07; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
  - Martha Jackson, 1958-08-27; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:51; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
  - Martha Jackson, Ground Squirrel Hunting Song, 1958-09-01; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:20; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Arthur; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine
  - Identification of recording, 1958; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:15; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; McClellan, Catharine
    Frederica de Laguna identifies contents of recordings on Reel 4. See Related Recordings.
    Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Potlatch--Alaska; Shamanism--Alaska
  - Long interview with old Douglas Billum, formerly of Chitina [1 of 2], 1958-07-26; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:02:30; Billum, Douglas; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; McClellan, Catharine
    Narratives interspersed with snatches of song. Recording runs slightly fast.
    Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska)
  - Long interview with old Douglas Billum, formerly of Chitina [2 of 2], 1958-07-26; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:57:29; Billum, Douglas; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; McClellan, Catharine
  - Douglas and Mary Anne Billum, both formerly of Chitina, 1958-07-28; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:25; Billum, Douglas; Billum, Mary Anne; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; McClellan, Catharine
    "1. Mary Ann drums, both sing a Tlingit song. 2. Ground Squirrel song, to bring good weatheer. 'Southweather clear all around I see'. Song is interrupted. 3. Second Groundsquirrel Song for good weather, follows without a break: 'tcisle, 'duya'ya'....' 4. Tlingit song. 'Ali......'"
    Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language
  - Copper Center Singing
    - Northway Potlatch Song, 1954-08-15; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:53; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Beginning of song missed in recording. Bill Joe drums; Markle Ewan, Jim McKinley, Ralph Sanford were the chief singers."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Potlatch--Alaska; Upper Tanana language
    - Northway War Dance, 1954-08-15; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:14; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Upper Tanana language
    - Northway Potlatch Song, 1954-08-15; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
    - Tlingit Song, 1954-08-15; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:33; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language
    - Tlingit or Eyak "Whale Gathering Song", 1954-08-15; 07-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:25; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Kate Sanford started the song, Bill Joe drumming. (7/23/60 it was explained that the song was sung slowly because Bill Joe had become mixed up). The song has a strongly accented beat; hu hu - and ends with clapping."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Eyak language; Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language
    - Eyak song, 1954-08-15; 07-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:20; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Eyak language; Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
    - TcAlali ha hi (drinking song), 1954-08-15; 07-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:18; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Up-the-Line song (i.e. from upper Copper River or Tanana River. 'Give me some more drink.'"
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Drinking songs--Alaska; Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
    - Love Song (probably Eyak), 1954-08-15; 07-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:58; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Martha Jackson and Bacille George identified it as 'down-the-line,' but the Chistochina people said it was 'up-the-line.'"
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Copper Center (Alaska); Eyak language; Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Love songs
    - Steven Northway's Christmas Tree mourning song for his wife, 1954-08-15; 07-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:36; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "(Made about 1954). 'Pity me, Christmas Tree.'"
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Upper Tanana language
    - Up-the-line song from Canada, about the swans leaving in the fall time, 1954-08-15; 07-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Beginning missed because of phone conversation in the hall. (Bacille George 8/28/58) called this a 'Happy New Year Song' from Up-the-line)."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Swans; Upper Tanana language
    - Northway Dancing Song, 1954-08-15; 07-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:08; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Jim McKinley started this Northway Dancing Song. (Martha Jackson identified this as a mourning song from up-the-line, but others as a dancing song)."
    - Song about Seagull (nAlbei) or Crow (sArani) eating something dead, caribou, fish, (dead man?), 1954-08-15; 07-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:59; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Variously identified as a song about Seagully (nAlbei) of Crow (sArani) eating something dead, caribou, fish, (dead man?).... It is apparently an Eyak song, in which the bird is addressed as 'grandfather' by the appropriate sib (?). Chistochina people in 1960 said it was sung by guests after a potlatch meal. 'We eat just like Crow and Seagull. We copy them.' (Possibly the bird is interchangeable, depending on which moiety is guest)."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Eyak Indians--Music; Eyak language; Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
    - Bille Song (Up-the-line "Worry Song"), 1954-08-15; 07-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:37; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
    - Old Up-the-line Dance Song, 1954-08-15; 07-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:40; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Identified by Bacille George 8/28/58 as an old Up-the-line Dance Song, which he had heard as a kid at a big potlatch at Upper Tonsina, when his father gave away $3000."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Potlatch--Alaska
    - Potlatch Song, Dance Song from Cordova, 1954-08-15; 07-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:37; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Identified by Bacille George as Tlingit."
    - Northway Song, 1954-08-15; 07-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:01; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
    - Dance Song with slow tempo, 1954-08-15; 07-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:09; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      A dance song identified as having a slow tempo. Identified by Bacille George as Tlingit.
    - Northway Song, 1954-08-15; 07-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:40; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
    - Northway Song (possibly Tanacross), 1954-08-15; 07-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:50; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Tanacross language; Upper Tanana language
    - Up-the-line dance, 1954-08-15; 07-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Recording missed initial two beats. Identified by Bacille George as an Up-the-line dance."
    - Tetlin Worry Song, 1954-08-15; 07-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:59; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Tetlin Worry Song (according to Bacille George). Maggie Joe started the singing. 'That's the biggest dance of them all.' The song belonged to Nancy George's cousin, a woman named May or xAtnilnan. 'My daddy, come back to your country. Oh my daddy.'"
    - Up-the-Line Dance, 1954-08-15; 07-22; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:58; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "(aiqat nil nAk -'tired, I quite half-way' can be heard."
    - Up-the-Line Dance, 1954-08-15; 07-23; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:05; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Maggy Joe suggested this song. Ralph Sanford says 'Go ahead and sing' in Athabaskan."
    - Good-By Song, 1954-08-15; 07-24; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:50; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
      "Good-By Song (ref. to Santa Claus ?) 'We see him back again. God bless you. I wish I see you again.' Way Up-the-line talk."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Christmas music; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
    - Old Up-the-Line Worry Song, 1954-08-15; 07-25; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:36; Craig, Oscar; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ewan, Markle; George, Bacille; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate; Sanford, Ralph
    - Identification of recording, 1954; 07-26; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:18; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; McClellan, Catharine
      "The recording of songs 1-12 [APSdigrec_1193 - APSdigrec_1202, APSdigrec_1303 - APSdigrec_1304] was made in the Alaska Native Brotherhood Hall, after a political meeting, at which Bruce Kendall of Valdez spoke of Statehood. The meeting was attended by men and women from Copper Center, Gulkana, and Chistochina. About 20 men and 10 women at the most joined in the singing. These included Jim McKinley and Oscar Craig of Copper Center, and Bill Joe and Ralph Sanford of Chistochina. Markle Ewan and two others were from Gulkana. The recording was interrupted by the failure of the power plant. Songs 13-25 [APSdigrec_1305 - APSdigrec_1317] and Side 2, songs 1-9 [APSdigrec_1319 - APSdigrec_1327], were recorded at our cabin, where we managed to get 13 Indians from Chistochina and Gulkana." Identification at end of tape of prior songs recorded on that tape. (APSdigrec_1193 - APSdigrec_1202, APSdigrec_1303 - APSdigrec_1317)
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music
    - Identification of recording, 1958; 07-27; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:17; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; McClellan, Catharine
      Provides identification information for subsequent recordings on reel [APSdigrec_1320 - APSdigrec_1336].
    - Love Song, 1958-08-15; 07-28; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:40; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "This seems to have been started by Maggy Joe. Her sister, Kate Sanford was convulsed with laughter. (Possibly the song is connected with Mentasta Pete's relatives; or from Dawson.) Chistochina people, 7/23/60, gave the words as 'Come back, honey'."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Love songs
    - Love Song, 1958-08-15; 07-29; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "Jim McKinley and Martha Jackson thought this was a Love song from Dawson - possibly made up by Mentasta Pete's nephew. Supposedly it was answered by the next song."
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Copper Center (Alaska); Han language; Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Love songs
    - Joe Nicolai's Song, 1958-08-15; 07-30; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:37; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "Martha Jackson and Jim McKinley identified this as a worry song belonging to Joe Nicolai, Elizabeth Pete's father. There is obviously some confusion of identification."
    - Dancing Song, 1958-08-15; 07-31; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:34; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      Song started by Bill Joe.
    - Santa Claus Song, 1958-08-15; 07-32; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:18; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "Jim McKinley was a kid when he heard this song. They first saw Santa Claus in Dawson, but were afraid of him. This seems to have been when they had a potlatch for Jim's uncle. Recorded comments: 'That's a ghost song - k'iyegi.' ... 'Too high.'"
      Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Ahtena language; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Upper Tanana language
    - Indian Schottische or Caribou Dancing Song, 1958-08-15; 07-33; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:15; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "There is a double drum beat. It comes from Dawson. The dancers imitate caribou pawing through the snow for food. (Identified by Mentasta people)."
    - Dawson Dancing Song, 1958-08-15; 07-34; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "'hwu' hu' hu' 'Eli'a!' Kate Sanford: 'That's the last one.'"
    - Cordova Dance Song, 1958-08-15; 07-35; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:31; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "Jim McKinley and Martha Jackson identified this as a Tlingit song, although Bill Joe called it Eyak. In 1960 Mentasta and Chistochina people again identified it as Eyak. The words mean 'good time,' and the singers make motions as if paddling a canoe. (de L comments on the tape 'beautiful song.'). Jim and Martha said that this version was wrong, and recorded correct version as [APSdigrec_1329]."
    - Whitehorse or Northway sARani (Crow) Song, 1958-08-15; 07-36; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:52; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; Joe, Bill; Joe, Maggie; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim; Sanford, Kate
      "'ali hei' and clapping at the end. The crow sits down in a trap. Jim McKinley was critical of Bill Joe's singing. The latter admitted in 1960 that he had cut it off short."
  - Cordova Tlingit Song, 1958-08-16; 07-37; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:03; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim
    "(Supposedly correct version of [APSdigrec_1327]). Jim learned it from Gus Heeney who died in 1917 or 1918. (The words are definitely Tlingit).... Recorded by Jim McKinley (who has reputation of being best singer and dancer at Copper Center) and Martha Jackson, after they had listened to earlier recordings on this reel 8/16/58"
    Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language
  - Funny Story Song, 1958-08-16; 07-38; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:01; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine; McKinley, Jim
    "The words are in both Tlingit and English. (Mean ??: "I don't thank you. You give me a funny story. Not a funny story....? I believe that all right. You been Cook's Inlet (or Klukshu?)" - deL's translation. Chistochina and Mentasta people in 1960 said this song would be sung when resting from dancing at a potlatch." "Recorded by Jim McKinley (who has reputation of being best singer and dancer at Copper Center) and Martha Jackson, after they had listened to earlier recordings on this reel 8/16/58"
    Ahtena Indians--Music; Ahtena Indians--Social life and customs; Copper Center (Alaska); Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Music; Tlingit language
  - Na'ina (Song Sparrow) Song, 1958-08-16; 07-39; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:23; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Jackson, Martha; McClellan, Catharine